Australia is a fascinating continent. As the driest continent
in the world apart from Antarctica, its no surprise that Australia
is home to the second largest desert of the inhabited earths continents,
remaining only behind the Sahara of northern Africa.
In scale and scope, the great australian desert
spans more than a third of the continent and is larger in size
than the entirety of Kazakhstan. And its partially because of
this desert that Australia itself, despite being the 6th
largest country in the world in terms of land, is only the
53rd largest in terms of people, with a modest
population of less than 26 million citizens,
were around the same size as North Korea. But within this
vast, inhospitable and empty desert,
at the precise geographic center of the australian
continent, exists a surprising and relatively
unknown secret of enormous geopolitical
importance. One of the largest overseas
military bases of the United States of America,
operated by the Central Intelligence Agency, the national Security Administration,
and the National Reconnaissance Office. With a full 800 combined
personnel, the base is located nearby to the small australian
town of Alice Springs, population just 26,000
or so people. But besides for that, there is no larger
town that exists anywhere, anywhere nearby to this base,
within a zone of about 700,000 km²,
roughly equivalent in area to the us state of Texas.
So to say that this american intelligence base, with hundreds of american
intelligence officers operating within the dead center of Australia
is a remote location would be an incredible understatement.
From the small australian town of Alice Springs, if you take
a short drive just ten minutes or so to the southwest,
youll quickly run into various threatening signs,
like this one, warning you to turn your car around and proceed no
further, or else face some vague consequences.
Just beyond these signs is, of course, the top secret
joint intelligence base of Pine Gap, run by both the american
and australian governments. And unless youve watched the Netflix series about
this base going under the same name, youve probably never even heard
of this place, or knew that such an important, important american operation
existed in the middle of the australian outback and
going under the more official codename of Project Rainfall.
It has a very long and mysterious history
here, going back decades into the past. You see,
as the global cold war between the United States and the Soviet Union
intensified during the 1960s, both nations began
sending up satellites into space with the launching of the earliest
intelligence gathering satellites. There was a recognition
that real time command and control over these platforms were necessary,
and data collection to monitor geopolitical adversaries
from afar was required. An american base to operate these
american intelligence and spy satellites operating over the planets
eastern hemisphere could have theoretically been constructed anywhere but
the precise geographic center of the australian
continent was chosen for a number of strategically important factors.
First, the sheer isolation of such a base
deep within the continental interior of Australia, more than 900
km away from the nearest coastline, ensured that
any potential spy ships from foreign nations passing around would
be incapable of intercepting any of the signals coming down
to the base from the satellites. Second, the base would be
located deep within Australia, a country who was very
friendly and allied towards the United States and far away
from any major australian population centers around the coasts.
And third, and perhaps most importantly, the location
where the station would be built required the base of the floor and surrounding
hills to not exceed six degrees at the precise
coordinates of pine gaps location in the center of Australia
at latitude 23.8 degrees south and longitude
133.74 degrees east.
The ability would be gained to allow for high connectivity with satellites
stationed as far as 60 degrees east and as far
east as 153 degrees west,
effectively covering the entirety of China, North Korea,
the indian subcontinent, and a significant portion
of the then Soviet Union. In short, it was a very
logically chosen location to construct a satellite intelligence base
at. And as a result, by late 1966,
the american and australian government signed a treaty calling for the
creation of a us satellite surveillance base in Australia,
which eventually became the modern pine gap,
where operations began in 1970 with the relocation
of hundreds of american families to the center of the outback.
But there was another, larger intelligence alliance
at work here that led to the creation of the base as well known as
the Five Eyes. This is an intelligence alliance of
the five major english speaking democracies around the world
of the United States, United Kingdom, Canada, Australia,
and New Zealand. Created during the fires of the Second World
War and expanded during the Cold War, this alliance
structure enables all member states intelligence agencies to easily
cooperate with each other and share all of their worldwide
data. As the cold War continued to rage and new threats
to the United States emerged. Like the Peoples Republic of China,
Vietnam, and later on, Iraq and Afghanistan, Pine Gap
continued to play a pivotal role in providing intelligence while dramatically
growing in size to the point where today it boasts nearly
440 separate antennas across the site and has operated
at least nine geosynchronous satellites owned by various
us spy agencies over the past 45 years.
Now, what makes these kinds of satellites uniquely well suited to
the mission of intelligence gathering is that within a geosynchronous
orbit, they travel in the same direction as the earths
rotation and therefore retain the exact same orbital
period as that of the earths rotation, which effectively just means
that they view the exact same portion of the surface
at all times, as if theyre sort of fixed in position on
the map. This is in stark contrast to satellites that operate
in lower Earth orbits which circle around the planet, often multiple
times a day, and move at a relative pace much
faster. One of the unique advantages of a geosynchronous
orbit for a spy satellite is that within this range,
it can see an enormous amount of the earths surface all
at once. In fact, if you were to go and do all the math and
run the calculations for this, it turns out to be just a tad
bit less than half of the earths entire surface.
This, of course, makes it incredibly easy for the spy
satellite above to gather a vast amount of
information from a very large area beneath it. And so
today there are three of these types of geosynchronous
spy satellites known to be operated from pine gap
all at the same line of latitude. Orion five above
the western Indian Ocean, Orion seven at the western tip
of the indonesian island of Sumatra and Orion three
just west of the indonesian island of Sulawesi.
Each of these three geosynchronous satellites sit in
an altitude of about 36,000 km above
the earths surface at these precisely coordinates.
And they each collect an incredibly wide range of electronic
signals from the earths surface beneath them, like radio communications,
radar emissions, microwave transmissions, missile telemetry,
satellite and cell phone transmissions, and even more. These three
satellites effectively grant american intelligence agencies,
and therefore the intelligence of all the five Eyes member states,
an incredible degree of satellite coverage across
every single area of modern US critical strategic
concern from western Africa, across the Middle East,
Ukraine, Russia, Iran, Afghanistan,
China and North Korea. More than half of the earths
surface outside of the polar regions. Once data from these regions
is received by the satellites, their information is relayed via a signal
back to the pine gap base in the center of Australia and then
disseminated from there towards the various intelligence agencies
of the five Eyes member states like the american CIA and
british Mi six. And while controversial at times,
the american intelligence capabilities that are granted by satellite sites
around the world like pine Gap are unmatched
by any other intelligence agency in the world.
And while most of what these satellites do is top secret
and highly classified, we all know that launching those satellites,
maintaining them up there and gathering all that data from the surface below
is an incredibly difficult feat to accomplish.
And if youre anything like me, then youre probably curious how
satellites like these actually work. And more to the point,
how anything actually works. Understanding the difficult
to understand is the very essence of STEM fields.
But for a lot of us and myself included. STEM subjects like
engineering and math and make this seemingly impossible possible
have never come as easy to understand.
But luckily we can all get our own little
dose of scientific learning every day now from brilliant
whether youre looking to learn something completely new or youre just trying
to brush up on a few topics, the best way to learn
anything is by actually doing the work yourself.
And theres no better place to do that than on brilliant.
You see, brilliant is an interactive stem learning platform that helps
you learn concepts by working through them in a visual,
hands on and easy to comprehend way. And you can get started on
any number of courses, from more basic concepts like the physics of
the everyday and casino probability, to significantly
more advanced fields like computer science, electricity and chemistry.
But regardless of which subject you choose to learn about, you get to learn
at your own pace. You can learn on the go with their mobile app
and and most importantly of all, you get to actually enjoy the
rewarding process of learning and understanding cool
new things about our reality. And if
you ever get stuck on a particular question, brilliant never punishes
you or impedes any of your progress. Instead theyll give you
an in depth explanation to help guide you along your learning path.
And best of all, you can try out brilliant right now completely for
free with the link down below in the description or by clicking the button
thats here on screen right now. The first 200 people to sign
up will also get 20% off of brilliant premium for
an entire year of wonderful stem learning. And as always,
thank you so much for watching.